<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevv yeeres gift The courte of ciuill courtesie: fitly furnished with a plesant porte of stately phrases and pithie precepts: assembled in the behalfe of all younge gentlemen, and others, that are desirous to frame their behauiour according to their estates, at all times, and in all companies: thereby to purchase worthy praise, of their inferiours: and estimation and credite amonge theyr betters. Out of Italian, by S.R. Gent.</title>
            <author>S. R. (Simon Robson), d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846160</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 351:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevv yeeres gift The courte of ciuill courtesie: fitly furnished with a plesant porte of stately phrases and pithie precepts: assembled in the behalfe of all younge gentlemen, and others, that are desirous to frame their behauiour according to their estates, at all times, and in all companies: thereby to purchase worthy praise, of their inferiours: and estimation and credite amonge theyr betters. Out of Italian, by S.R. Gent.</title>
                  <author>S. R. (Simon Robson), d. 1617.</author>
                  <author>Mont. Prisacchi Retta, Bengalassa del, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18, 18-38 [i.e. 40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Ihones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.R. = Simon Robson. Sometimes wrongly attributed to Samuel Rowlands.</note>
                  <note>Purports to be a translation from Bengalassa del Mont. Prisacchi Retta, but is actually by Robson.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The court of ciuill curtesie, for younge gentlemen.</note>
                  <note>Pages 39 and 40 misnumbered 31 and 38.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courtesy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:1"/>
            <p>A NEVV YEERES GIFT.</p>
            <p>THE COVRTE of ciuill Courteſie:</p>
            <p>Fitly furniſhed with a pleſant porte of ſtately phraſes and pithie precepts: aſſembled in the behalfe of all <hi>younge Gentlemen, and others, that are deſirous to frame their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour according to their eſtates, at all times, and in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereby to purchaſe worthy <hi>praiſe; of their inferiours: and</hi> eſtimation and credite <hi>amonge theyr</hi> betters.</p>
            <p>Out of Italian, by S. R. Gent.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by Richard Ihones. 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:2"/>
            <head>To the flouriſhing Youthes, and Courteous young Gentlemen of England, and to all others that are deſirous, and louers of Ciuile Courteſie: R. I. the Printer hereof, wiſheth an happie New yeere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and many: to the pleaſure of God, and their owne hartes deſire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Courteous young Gentlemen, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon your great Curteſie: I haue been ſo bolde as to preſent your eſtate, in token and wiſh of an happie new yeere, with theſe the firſt fruites of my poore Preſſe, finiſhed ſince the cumming in of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Surely, the traueill of a Gentleman whom I know not, no not ſo mutch as by name, much leſſe by perſon: And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the copie, as he that brought it vnto me made reporte, that it was tranſlated out of the Italian, by a Gentleman, a freende of his, deſiring me that it might be printed. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwaies deſirous to farther the ſtudie, and procure the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites of all men, by publiſhing bookes of ſemblable argument: thought good to dedicate the ſame vnto you, iudging it in this reſpect a preſent more meete for your moſte flouriſhing degree: for that I perceiue it to haue beene firſt written by a Noble and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> perſonage of Italy, and directed vnto his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, a young Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo of noble parentage, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conforming of his behauiour at his entrace into the Court, as it may appeare by his Epiſtle hereafter following. Now for that this caſe is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto moſt of you, and aboue all other the ſtudie of ciuell Curteſie, moſt incident vnto your calling, I am the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er to craue your Courteous countenance, and friendly fauour in accepting the ſame now in Engliſh at my hands, as a teſtimonie of my ſeruiceable heart, and good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towards you. And that receiuing it now fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me as your owne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you would vouchſafe of your great curteſie, to take both me and it in to your aſſured protection: and to defend both the preſent, and him that offereth it, from the ſpightfull toungues of malicious carpers. And in ſo dooing, you ſhall euermore binde me to emploie what traueill and ſeruice I can, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncing and pleaſuring of your moſt excellent degree.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell in the Lord.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:3"/>
            <head>The Cenſure of a friende, concerning this worke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OVr Parents well deſerue the pricke of price,</l>
               <l>Who giue vs life which we had not before.</l>
               <l>The teachers care deſerues great thanke likewiſe,</l>
               <l>Who traines the childe, and giues the learned lore:</l>
               <l>Immortall praiſe we ought giue him therefore.</l>
               <l>Some ſtrife hath bin in reſpect of theſe things,</l>
               <l>Who beſt deſerues of theſe two Noble ſprings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Though one giue life, the other learning lendes,</l>
               <l>Let reaſon rule, let wit this matter ſcan.</l>
               <l>And things are iudgde, according to their endes,</l>
               <l>And prouerbe olde ſayes manners makes the man.</l>
               <l>The vitall ſprite muſt yeeld to learning than.</l>
               <l>Wherfore you youthes, ſprunge vp from gentle line,</l>
               <l>Vnto this Court your courteous eares incline.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ This Court, the which of Curteſie takes name,</l>
               <l>Declares what port eche Gentill ſhall inſue.</l>
               <l>At all aſſayes how he himſelfe ſhall frame,</l>
               <l>To follow what, and what for to eſchue.</l>
               <l>Thrice happie he whom God ſhall ſo indue.</l>
               <l>A thing of weight, and wun for ſimple price,</l>
               <l>Reiect by fooles, but purchaſt by the wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:3"/>
            <head>Bengalaſſa del Mont. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacchi Retta, vnto Seig. Princiſea Ganzar Moretta. For his behauiour. vz.</head>
            <head type="sub">To my Nephew Seig. Princiſca Ganzar Morretta.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T MY LAST BEING at Priſacchi, vnderſtanding by your fathers talke, that he minded to haue you a while in the Court, where hee hath ſpent the better part of his life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and becauſe it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented with all ſortes of companies, as any place in Italy is. I haue directed this little booke, which if you read and marke diligently, ſhall be as it were a guide, to leade you from a number of ſnates which you may be trapt withall, alſo for your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour in all companies: with many other things fit to be knowen of younge Gentlemen, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for ſutch as haue not beene conuerſant in all companies.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare ye well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Contentes of the Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HOw a younge Gentleman may behaue himſelfe in all companies: and be prepared for ordinary en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainements, and to get a good opinion and credite among his bettars. <hi>Chap. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man ſhall behaue himſelfe in had companye, and among ſutch roiſters as will offer familiaritye with him, will he or no: and firſt a gueſſe of ſutch meanes as they will vſe thereto. <hi>Chap. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man ſhall anſwer to the prayſe &amp; thankes, &amp; curteſies ſeriouſly offred by his betters or equals. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man ſhall acquite himſelfe towardes noble perſons, that ſhall either for his fréendes ſake, or his owne, offer him curteſies: or aſſure him of friendſhip, willing him in all chaunces to be bolde with him. <hi>Chap. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ Howe when the foreſayde ſpéeches be offered by a Noble perſon pleaſantly, that is of acquaintaunce: which muſt be alſo pleaſantly anſwered. <hi>Chap. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to an equall, or but little better: béeing a friend and familiar. <hi>Chap. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man ſhall take thankes of a noble perſon. <hi>ca. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man may giue thankes to his betters and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals. <hi>Chap. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ What manners be requiſitie of the Table, and what to be ſhunned: what is to be conſidered in the waſhing before Dinner, and in the ſitting downe, is ſet foorth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of this Direction. <hi>Chap. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How a man ſhall pacifie his friend, his better, or his equall: if he haue giuen him vnwillingly any cauſe of offence. <hi>Chap. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Now a man ſhall ſhift off reproches or tauntes offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red betwéene ſporte and earneſt: by enuious and ſcornefull perſons that will ſéeme to doo it ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly as the other ſhall haue the taunt, and yet at his owne pleaſure will denie it. <hi>Chap. 11.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11108:4"/>
            <head>The Courte of ciuill Curteſie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>How a yonge Gentilman may behaue himſelfe in all companies, and be prepared for ordinary entertainments, and to get a good oppinion and credit among his betters.</head>
               <head>Chap. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt hee hath to conſider, that the</hi> lacke of good behauiour, which is a comely audacitie, with out a ſauſie preſumption (which argueth diſcréete iudgement and wiſedome) maketh his inferiour to be his equal, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his equall his better, till himſelfe hath attayned not only the habit of béeing the like, but the time to make himſelfe know to be the like. Therefore if he ſhall light in the company of any, whoſe liuing and birth is worſe then his owne, and yet perceyueth the other for his wiſedome and grauitie to be well eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of by others, it becommeth the yonge Gentleman to giue him the place (or at leaſt with inſtance to offer it him) but yet with ſuch a modeſt audacitie, mingled with a ſmiling grace, and curteous ſpéeche, neither too lowde nor whiſpering, as the reſt of the company may well perceiue: it is the vertues, and not the man that is preferred, and that it is offered rather of a curteous diſpoſition, then of a ſhéepiſhe ſimplicitie, which wilbe the better vnderſtanded if he ſhall vtter ſome familier ſpéech in yelding the place at the doore, <hi>as thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11108:5"/>I pray you goe, for I looue to follow the ſteppes of mine elders. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt néedes goe, for I cannot away to goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On, on I pray you, you bee the next the doore. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you goe not wee ſhall ſtriue all day, for I will not. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You make too mutch adoe for ſo ſmall a matter: And at the placing at the table, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will you ſyt ſir, and I wilbe next you? <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not I by your leaue. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a one will needes haue you by him. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſhall not rule me till you come to your owne houſe. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place is fitter for you then for me. <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Goe too, ſhall we ſtriue all day like women.</p>
               <p>And if it be one that be of great eſtimation, either for office, or ancientie, and will yet of too much curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie refuſe the place, then it ſhalbe beſt to ſit downe firſt, but to take a lower place either on the other ſide, or on the ſame ſide. But there (by the way) it is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that this curteſy is not ſo preciſely to bee vſed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at common tables, where eche man payeth equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his meale, nor yet at ordenary tables in the Court: for in either of theſe two places, except diuerſity of degree make difference, men vſe not this curioſitie: then this aforeſayd at the table, is when men meete in their equals or inferiours houſes, in which it is to be conſidered that the owners of the tables muſt beare the ſwaye of placing, if he be the better or equall. Howbeit, if the owner ſhall call or place one (either not knowing who ought or not caring who doe) that is inferiour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie way, ſauing for wealth, in ſuch a caſe, the younge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11108:5"/>Gentleman ſhall doo well not to tarry till other be ſet, not abyding the placing of the owner: but takinge his nexte companion to ſet himſelf downe firſt, rather two or thrée lower, then he ſhould be the next to his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: whereby the owner ſhalbe (in ſylence) taught to conſyder better an other time.</p>
               <p>And he muſt not ſuffer himſelfe to be remoued any higher, that he may kéepe the owner ſtill in doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſo placed himſelfe of miſlike or of good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But if there be much adoe made, and that he finde the owner to finde his owne errour: then it will be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy to couller the fact with good words pleaſauntly, <hi>As thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why? thinke you that I can eate no meate but at the vpper ende of the bourd. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you hinder not my good happe, I am where I like. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you giue me leaue to ſit where I like. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you trouble not your ſelfe, you ſhall ſée vs as merrye here as you be there. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As long as I finde good meat I neuer vſe to ſtudye for my place, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I warrant you if I had not liked this place, I would haue bin ſo bold as choſen an other. But if happen the owner of the houſe, be ſo groſſe and careles, that hee either doo not or will not finde any miſlike of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: then would I wiſhe in ſuch a caſe, the young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be furniſhed with ſome guirding ſpeeches or els ſome pleaſaunt ſcoffes, to countenaunce out the matter, with thoſe that ſyt by him, that the reſt may ſée he choaſe the place in ſcorne of the other, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am happely placed here, for if I had mounted any higher, I had béen cleane out of countenaunce. <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11108:6"/>We wilbe as merrie here, as though we ſat at the vpper ende of the bourd: or to ſome companion, that ſits next abooue by the younge Gentlemans placing, <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you behaue not your ſelues gently, and be good to vs of the ſecond meſſe, we will kéepe you from moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the next time. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beware freinds, pride will haue a fall: ſpeake not ſo lowde your betters be in place. And to conclude, to make as much mirthe and paſtime as may be all the meale. But if a man be in a noblemans houſe, or a Knight of great reputacion, then he muſt be contented for that time, as pleaſeth them. But he may the nexte time, take as good a place as he can with modeſtie get, and when he is from the bourd, not looſe any place that reaſon or courage can aduaunce him to. For as no man is diſgraced by giuing (of his curteſy) place to whom he liſt, ſo to haue it taken from him by others being his right, is an abaſement not to be ſuffred, if a man can take it either by ſlight or courage.</p>
               <p>Now that this young Gentleman, may know in what ſorte he may accompany himſelfe with all ſorts, and to all eſtates: he ſhall know, that the eldeſt ſonne of a Knight while his father liueth, may count himſelfe equall with a Gentleman of .cc. li. land rent of aſſiſe (for ſo the Statute limiteth) and may offer himſelfe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with the beſt Squire, if his wit with a modeſt audacitie will ſerue him thereto, but not without ſome reuerent reſpectes in his ſpéeche: ſpecially if the ſayde Squier be of grauitie, and ſo of reputation, either for his wiſdome or office, as if he wil aſke a queſtion, <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you ſyr, what? where? or why is ſutch a thing? <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will it pleaſe you to doo, or haue ſuch a thing: and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11108:6"/>in his affirmation and negation to anſwer, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye ſir, no ſir. And if the other aſke him any queſtion, as whether he will doo this, or that. <hi>Then thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mary ſir I will tell you. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With a good will, if it pleaſe you, &amp;c. As the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall fall out. Howbeit theſe ſpéeches, if it be to no better then to the beſt Squier, or an ordinarie Knight be to be vſed, with ſuch a famillier kinde of pronunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as it may appeare to be vttred by him of his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy: meaning rather to giue them more then he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly néeded, then of any great difference he thinkes to be betweene them: ſpecially if they be ſutch, as he is not like any way, either to be in daunger of their hurt, or in néede of their help. And though theſe kinde of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpeeches néede not to be ſo curiouſly vſed, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, to one much his better, when they be once ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry familier: yet they become the ſpeaker ſo well, as if they be vſed with a good audacitie and familier coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, a man may vſe them to his inferiour, without any abacement or diſgrace at all to himſelfe, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to Ladies and Gentlewomen of credit.</p>
               <p>Then he hath to conſider that among yonge Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, or younge Noblemen, there needes no great curioſitie, but before a Barron, and ſo vpward, he may not be couered while he ſtandeth in his viewe, except the Nobleman bid him: vnleſſe that Nobleman vſe ſuch an ordinarie kinde of fellowſhip with all men (as he ſoeth) as meane as himſelfe vſe him with ſmall cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy: and yet he muſt way withall whether that good-fellowſhip bee withall men indifferently, or onely to ſuche as be his familliers: for ſutch as be Noble may make theyr companions whom they liſt, and the reſt though they ſhalbe better to ſuch companions, not to vſe euer the leſſe honour to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11108:7"/>And let this ſtand for a generall rule, that whatſoeuer familiarity a noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſhow to any his inferiour, yea though he profeſſe to make him his equall friend: let the inferiour ſtill beware of vſing himſelfe rudely, ſawcely or careleſly, eſpecially in the preſence of others, For though many to aſſure their inferiour of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, ſéeme to baniſh all curioſity: yet ſuch a one ſhalbe beſt eſtéemed, and longeſt hold friendſhip with his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that in all their greateſt familiarity can make it appeare to others that he dooth not forget, that he play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth or ieſteth with his ſuperiour. Which a man may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well doe and yet holde company in all manner of ſportes, teſtes, and paſtimes: then much more he that is a ſtraunger muſt haue the more regarde. And as it is good manner for a man in his owne houſe, or his friendes, if he be the beſt in the company, to offer inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement to any noble man: ſo in a ſtraunge place in the houſe of his better, though there be no better then himſelfe in the place, he may not preſume to beginne intertainment: but it is his part to be ready, and next the Nobleman in ſight, againſt it pleaſeth him to vſe him, till he ſéeth him accompanied with ſome others, or call ſome other to him: and if it be but open talke deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to paſſe away the time, then to helpe lengthen the ſame at his diſcretion: otherwiſe to finde ſome talke with others, and rather to ſtande or ſit, with a ſteddy and aſſured countenaunce, as though he were ſtudying ſome matter of waight, or harkening to others talke if it be not ſecret: then to accompanye him ſelfe with ſuch as be vnwoorthy of his company: and ſuch count I ſeruing men, and fooliſh doltiſh perſons though they be his betters. But when a man ſhall ſit ſtill and ſay nothing, he muſt be ſure to haue an aſſured cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, not gnawing any thing in his mouth, or playing with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11108:7"/>his legges, toes, or fingers, and to haue alwaies an eare and an eye about him, to here what is ſaide, and to be reddy if any part of an others talke, eyther by word or looke be addreſſed to him, that he may receiue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and winne in the talke: and though no ſuch cauſe be offred, yet it is a better grace to harken other folkes communication, then to be talking with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vaine credit: and if a man ſhall get him out of the way for lacke of countenance, when noble perſons or others of reputation be in the place: then will his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour lye in a waite for occaſion, and ſtep in, to bee of familiaritie before him.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, if talke be offered to this yonge Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilman by his better, he hath to conſider whether the ſame procéede of a deſire to paſſe away the time, and for want of other companie: or els (as ſome doo) becauſe they wilbe thought curteous, they will ſaye ſome thing to euerie body, but for feare of too much familiaritie, will not ſtay longe with their inferiour. To this laſt it ſhalbe good only to anſwer to the queſtion, adding ſome reaſon to verefie the ſame, but not to enter any new matter, nor to dilate any further in the old, then he ſhall perceiue him by his countenance and attentiuenes to heare without prouocation. But if the inferiour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that the talke is miniſtred vpon the firſt reſpect, that is to make entertainment: he muſt not onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all his demaunds, but enlarge the ſame to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt: And when he ſéeth his better pawſe, ſo that he turne not away warde (as though he would be gon from him) to inuent ſome matter of himſelf, to lengthen talke: And that he may the better doo ſo,<note place="margin">In any wiſe let a man ſhun as much as he can in his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments to ſpeake of himſelfe as to tell, what he hath ſaide or what he hath donne: for that will be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come of a deſire to tell his owne praiſe, except it be either to his very frend or els that it be ſomthing that thother is deſirous to here.</note> he muſt before hand haue enquired (of ſuch as come in his companie) if otherwiſe he cannot learne, what manner of country the ſtranger dwelleth in: from what place he commeth:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11108:8"/>and whither he is going: what paſtime or exerciſe be loueth. By which meanes he may redemaunde of the wearines, or pleſantnes of the iourney: of the fowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or fayrenes of the weather: whether the Country he dwelleth in ſerue commodiouſlye to the vſe of ſutch things as he delighteth in: whether the Gentlemen of that ſhyre be companiable in the like or not: and by this meanes, alſo he ſhalbe able ſo to vnderſtand of mo countries, and men, then he knowes, although he met with them as ſtraungers, yet he ſhall be prouided of ſumwhat to diſcourſe with them thereof. But if a man talke with his better, he muſt alwaies obſerue with what attentiuenes or willing minde the other giueth care to him, that he may leaue off, before the other be weary: and to be very héedefull that he ſpeake nothing affirmatiuely, but that himſelfe hath ſeene: but he may well ſay I haue harde, or I haue read, that this, or that is thus. And in tellyng any thing by hereſay, ſpecially to a ſtranger, he muſt reſpect thrée things, thone, that it ſound not to the diſpraiſe of any by name, except it be a thing openlie knowne, and yet the diſpraiſed may hap to be ſo neare a friend to him that ſhall heare it, as the teller ſhall get miſlike. The other is, that when they tell a tale of an other mans mouth, he forbeare to tell the name of his aucthor, eſpecially if he bee his freind, for if it ſhall ſéeme vnlikely though it be true, he ſhall bring his freinds credit in ſuſpect. The thyrde kinde is, that he neuer take vpon him in open preſence, to make any report of the ſayings or doings of his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, except they be ſuch as the company knoweth him to be familiarly acquainted with, for otherwiſe, he ſhall make himſelfe compared to them that talke of <hi>Robin Hoode</hi> and neuer ſhot in his bowe. Laſtly let him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make vp his entertaynements with the diſprayſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11108:8"/>or mocking of any, eyther preſent, or abſent, though he heare other doo the like, (except only in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his very aſſured freinds) and that for this reſpect. A yonge man muſt euer thinke that it is vnpoſſible for him to be ſo compleat in all perfections of béehauour, but that ſome thing remains in him worthy the laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at, if men ſhould not forbeare him in reſpect of time which brings experience to the wiſeſt, and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture too, euen ſome of the ſame defects which he ſeeth ſcoff at in an other, may be in himſelfe, vnknowen to himſelfe, or at leaſt others as ill: And therefore the wiſeſt way is, if his better ſéeme to deride any for his béehauour, to appeare by a ſmiling countenaunce to be of the ſame opinion: but in woords to eſcuſe it, if hee may, as if the dooings of him that is mocked ſhew ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be that baſhfulnes is the cauſe: if they ſhew rudenes, <hi>then thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Want of experience makes men erre. But if they be his equals, or inferiours that ſo ſcof, then merelye, <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go too ſyrs, many a one going about to mocke on be cares not for, dooth often touche himſelfe or his néere fréende, <hi>or by a ſimilitude thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On, on, ſaw yée neuer any or this, that litfe vp a Weapon to ſtryke another and hyt himſelfe. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take your pleaſure my maſters, I warrant you therebe that doo as mutche for vs, as we doo for them. And in déede there cannot any greater praiſe be giuen to any man, then this, that one ſhall neuer heere him ſpeake yll of anye, and hearyng yll, wyll make the beſt of it. Howbéeit, it is bothe within the limmittes of honeſtye, wyſoome, and fréendſhip,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11108:9"/>any man to diſcourſe plainelie with his freind, either of the miſbehauiour, or vnhoneſt dealynges of any: that on the one ſide he may ſhew himſelfe a miſliker of ill perſons, and alſo make his freinde ware of them. And by the way it is to be noted, that there be thrée ſorts of people, which whoſoeuer ſhall ſcoffe &amp; ſkornel at, or els ieſt with them, further then the compas of curteſy ſhall permit, ſhall receiue more diſgrace by dooing it, then the other ſhall by ſuffering it.</p>
               <p>The fyrſt is women, or ſimple milde ſprited men: for women muſt neuer be ieſters, nor ſcoffers, further then the bounds of modeſtie and curteſie, to make the time paſſe away the more pleaſantly: ſo that a man to ieſt ſo farre with them as they may not for ſhame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, nor for inſufficiencie quarrell for, wilbe accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a diſhonorable battell, wherin the vanquiſhed hath more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them the vanquiſher:<note place="margin">This is ment by ſharpe and taunting ieſtes when a man will ſeeke to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace or put one out of countenance by ieſtes.</note> for it is better to yéelde with ſilence, then to contend for the maſterie in vnfytting termes, and to offer the milde ſpréeted man the like: that fynding himſelfe agréeued, hath neither the wit to ſhift of it in words, neither the courrage to reuenge i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in déede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame predicament that the woman is: And all noble mindes doo of their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies forbeare to offend, and offer to defend all thoſe that either cannot (as féeble perſons) or ought not (as the feminine ſexe) reuenge or defend themſelues.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſorte that may not be mocked or ſcoffed at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſons, and ſuch as be deformed, for want either of bewtie, fanour, or other blemiſhes in their ſhape, ſtature or linunes: becauſe none of theſe things be faults of their owne making, neither lieth it in their power to amend them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So as we ought rather to bee mooued thereby too thanke the maker or vs all, for dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo much better with vs, then with them, then to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11108:9"/>ſcorne or depraue them for that they cannot helpt. And if withall we will conſider, that the deformities of the minde, be ſo much fowler then thoſe of the body, as the ſoule is of more value, and ought to be more vniforme: it wilbe a good meane to make the outwarde defects of others, very ſmall in reſpect of our owne, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but he greater and many moe, and conſequently, rather to eſcuſe them, then deſpiſe them.</p>
               <p>The thyrd ſorte that cannot beare, neither ought to be offred ſcoffing, mocking, or leſting: be thoſe that be in miſcrie: either by ſorrow, impriſonment, or any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, by loſſe of fréen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſubſtance or credit: For theſe be things ſent from God, to put vs in remembrance, that we hauing deſerued as ill, may fall into the like when it pleaſeth him: and in the meane times be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects for vs, to practiſe our compaſſion and charitie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But there may riſe this queſtion, ſéeing that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique enterteinments, ſpecially among younge folkes, are continued more often with ſpéeche of little impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then with matters of waight: How a man find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe in ſuch companie, as are neither fit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of matters of wiſdome, nor yet to be imparted with of his owne priuate affaires, ſhall finde matter ſuffici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to paſſe the time in companie? For anſwer héereunto, let this be remembred, that where as I haue ſayd, that men muſt take heede in their open talke, how they be to buſy in bringing in the ſayings and dooings of noble perſons, leaſt the hearers ſhould thinke that he arrogateth to himſelfe greater acquaintance with ſuch, then in déede he hath: or els, leaſt comming to theyr eares, they ſhould miſlike that their inferiours ſhould make them their talking ſtockes. Yet if he that ſhall ſo introduce (by way of confirmation, enſample, or ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) the ſaying of his betters, be ſure that it ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11108:10"/>wiſdom &amp; praiſe, or at the leaſt, ſome pleaſantneſſe with but any harme or diſgrace to any other, he may well vſe it in his talke: Prouided that he ſpeake it as by hereſay, ercept he haue it in deede by his owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Alſo women and deformed perſons, may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanted and ieſted with, if their wit be ſutch as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the like, and can in good ſporſe enterchaunge in the ſame manner. Prouided that the boundes of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie be obſerued (that is) that there be no cauſe of blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing giuen.</p>
               <p>Alſo, all men in ſickenes, priſonment, or pouertie, be not miſerable, for they be only ſuch that haue an afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted minde: for ſome can ieſt and ſcoffe at their owne diſgraces, thinking thereby to make them ſeeme the leſſe in other mens eyes, while they appeare no heuier, then ſutche as themſelues can pleaſantly beare: And ſutch had rather be reſted with then pittied.</p>
               <p>The fault therefore that can be committed in theſe perſons, is the mocking them behinde their backes, or deſpiſing them, which no man ought to ſhew to any, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be to them that be knowen to be impudent and ſhameleſſe perſons, or elſe ſuch as be knowen to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwenyng fooles in their owne conceyte, and be ſuche as doo the like by others. Of theſe a man may talke his pleaſure, as well of them, as with them, without any diſgrace to himſelfe: Prouided that if any quarrell riſe thereby, he be as readies of courage to maintaine it with his hand, as of ſpeeche to vtter it with his tongue.</p>
               <p>Alſo a man may teſt with his very famillier freind: if he finde him of diſpoſicion willing to beare it, and of wit ſufficient to aunſwer it. And it ſkilles not what he lay to his charge, though it be diſhoneſtie: prouided that it be not true that is imputed to him, or if it be true that the other be ſo braſen faced as he will not be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11108:10"/>aſhamed of it.</p>
               <p>I would not aduiſe any man to ieſt mutch with his inferiours, vnleſſe they be ſuch as he knoweth, both can and will vſe a reſtraint of ouer male partnes. For if a Gentilman ſhould be ſaucely vſed by ieſt, by his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he cannot eſcape diſgrace, whether he beare with it, or quarrell for it: but bearing it is beſt, and to ſhut it vp rather with a pleaſant nip, then any way to ſeeme angry, if the mirth he of his owne beginning.</p>
               <p>And thus much for a taſte how a man may paſſe his talke among his betters and equals, in a ſtraunge place, and in ſtraunge company.</p>
               <p>Yet this admonition more I muſt adde, that who ſo in his entertainments ſhall endeuour to tell any tale to mooue laughter (ſpectally in ſtraunge companie) had néede to be ſure that it carrye that life or quickneſſe with it, as he be not ſo much deceaued of his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he be faine himſelfe to laugh alone: for that wil be ſo great a diſgrace, as in ſtéede of laughing at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they will ſmile in theyr ſtéeues at him: and therfore to ſhun that he muſt beware that he take not in hand to tell any thing for fooliſh, that is not folly: nor for wiſe that hath couller of folly: nor for a wonder that is not wonderfull: nor for rare, that is common: for want of experience may deceiue all theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11108:11"/>
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall beehaue himſelfe in bad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and among ſuch Royſters as will offer familiaritie with him, will he or no: and firſt a gueſſe of ſutch meanes as they will vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</head>
               <head>¶ The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heir manner is lightly, if they finde a younge Gentleman that is to bee of a fayre liuing, if they ſée him ſoberly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, after they haue made their deuiſe among themſelues, how euery man ſhall play his part, that one of them ſhall pretend great grauitie with him, and he ſhall praiſe him to the cloudes, and become his councellour: another ſhall tel wonders to his fellow, to ſée if between them they can catche a Woodcocke of him.</p>
               <p>Another (if the fyrſt deuice ſerue not) will go about in ſcoffing and iollying ſorte, to ſée if by putting them out of countenaunce, they can make him glad to bee of their faction, and to further the ſame, an other ſhall ſeeme to reprooue all them. And as though he were the plaineſt honeſt man in the company, he will offer to quarrell with them in his behalfe: and all will be done with ſuch oathes and ſad lookes, as for all a man is warned (he ſhall doubt) whither there he any that meane good faith or not. And it may be indéed that ſome of theſe may meane honeſtly, and that may be the firſt and the laſt, (for thother two bewray themſelues) and therfore a man muſt vſe thoſe he doubts of in ſuch ſort, as he neither vtterly reiect them, meaning well, nor ſhew him ſo fooliſh, as at the firſt or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11108:11"/>ſhall take vpon him to praiſe or aduiſe him, let him conſider what reputation and countenaunce he is of, or if they be ſutch, as be of lyuing, and withall can be contented to liue within the compaſſe of his owne, then there is the leſſe ſuſpition to he had of him, further then this: that euery wiſe man will ſuſpect any man that too mutch praiſeth him (except it be his famillier and aſſured freind) but for the more ſuerty it ſhalbe wel to anſwer in this manner: not ſeriouſly, but ſomewhat myling and famillierly. Me thinks it very good that you and I were neuer better acquainted: for by that meanes you maye be kept in that good oppion which now ye ſéeme to conceiue of me, either by hereſay, or by your owne gueſſe, leaſt by too much conuerſation you be made to chainge your minde: but in the meane time I thanke you, bothe of your good liking, and of the good aduice you profer me: for I ſhall euer haue néede of good counſell: and if there be any other thing (becauſe I am vnfurniſhed to requite you in the ſame) wherein I may pleaſure you as much, you ſhal finde me as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And ſo to ſhift him of, and fall into ſome other talke, enquiring of this or that, him or her, as the obiect of the eye or minde ſhall lead.</p>
               <p>Now for the wonder tellers, I finde thrée or foure fortes of them: the one ſort onely vpon pleaſure to paſſe away the time, not looking to be beléeued of any, but to be iolled within the like: With theſe the beſt way is meerely to take vpon you to know it to be true, and to ad to it ſomething that maye make it ſéeme more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely. And though it ſhould ſo fall out that the tale ſhould be true, that to another ſeemeth either vnlike or vnpoſſible: yet is there no harme done, in not ſéeming to beleeue it, while I know no reaſon to lead me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: mary, if after the ſame with ſad aſſeueracion and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11108:12"/>be iuſtified to be true: a man muſt of curteſie ſeeme to eredit their othes, but neuer the more to cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it likely, except they can ſhew ſo by reaſon.</p>
               <p>Thother ſorte for that they would be taken for doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or knowers of great things, will for their owne glorie tell maruels, either of ſuch things as they haue done, or ſuch things as they haue ſeene in ſtraung Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. And will thinke in déede, what by his ſolemne countenance, what by ſwearing and lying, eyther to be credited, or at leaſt that no man ſhall ſéeme to diſcredit them: and if any go about it to quarrell with them. In this caſe I would either ſay nothing, or if he ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his tale to me, whereby I muſt be drouen to ſays ſomething: I ſhould be in ſutch ſorte as I would ſéeme to ſoothe him in woordes, but others ſuch as I thought my fréends, ſhould perceiue by my countenance I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thought it pittie to put him out of his vaine, then was of the minde to beléeue all he ſayd. Yet that muſt he done ſo cunningly too, that if the teller or the hearers ſhould, to picke a thanke, chalenge me for the ſame: I would be able (if I liſt) without denying anye thing I ſayde or did, or make the blame light on them that would goe about to diſtaine my meaning, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can I not looke on ſuch a one, or ſpeake ſo, but that I muſt meane as ye would: it is you, me thinkes, that go about to bringe in queſtion that which no man els thought on, if I were as be, I would thanke you for that, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The thyrde, and the worſt of theſe wonder tellers, is he that in very déede maketh it his art, of purpoſe to catche Woodcockes, as they terme it, and they will vſe it either ſo conningly or ſo impudently, as they will make him, whom they hunt after to be a Foole in that pointe, or ſeeme a foole: for they will ſo mingle thinges
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11108:12"/>like to be true, or at the leaſt not impoſſible with things merely, faulſe and vnpoſſible: as if the hearer ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receiue all indifferently, or reiect all indifferently, he ſhall ſeeme either too ignorant, or too light of beleefe. And if he ſhall by iudgement ſcan and ſeuer the other from the other, and ſo condempne any parte, though not the whole: then ſwearing, flowting and quarreling, wilbe offered to iuſtifie the matter: and this it is, will they ſay) to tell a tale to him that hath neuer gon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then his mother and nurſery, to call for his pappe in a morning, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And then muſt the laſt man that I firſt ſpake of and is the fourth in this tragedie, ſteppe foorthe and tell his fellow he offreth the yong Gentleman too much wrong, and he ſhall not take it at his hands, &amp; himſelf will take his part, &amp; go into the Field either with him or for him.</p>
               <p>To ſhift bothe theſe of, the beſt way, if any will rid it, is firſt to let the other to tell all his lies, and to let him paſſe with a ſmile in the ſleeue, as they will call it, rather then to vſe either admiration, or negation: but if he be vrged to ſaye his oppinion, as he ſhall, if it be a verſe of courſe, then ſhortly to anſwer, <hi>thus: or the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay no more, but it may be true for me: for there be many things that ſéeme vnpoſſible, and yet prooue true Matters of faith may not be reaſoned on, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Me thinkes it is a very good tale, I meane not to ſcan any further on the matter. And theſe or the like woords may be vttered with ſuch a grace, as the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance may ſhew the minde, and yet the ſpeeche keepe them from quarrell. But if they wyll néedes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it to the vttermoſt: then he that ſhall ſeeme to ſet the yonge Gentleman a gog. and offer to be his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: he muſt of curteſie ſeeme to thanke him, but not be ſo vnwiſe hs accept him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11108:13"/>For no wiſe man will accept into his company, at ſuch a bargen, a ſtranger if he haue any of his freinds to make accompt of, though he ſuſpect no practiſe at all, but yet he muſt be put of with good words, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thanke you, you ſhall not néede to take the paine, for I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſed a fréend of mine,<note place="margin">There is a difference betweene ruffaly phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſuch reprochefull woords as expreſſe the fowleneſſe of the act or the ilneſſe of the perſon.</note> in theſe caſes (if I take any body with me) it muſt be he: I will quarrell with no body, but if any body haue any quarrell to me, I haue buſineſſe into ſutch a place, ſuch a day, at ſutche an hower: I will haue but my ſelfe and my man, or but my ſelfe and my friend, there he may finde me if he dare: and ſo aſmuch as may be to forbeare ruffainly words. But if any man be called by any reprochefull names, they muſt néedes be required both in termes and déedes, but after ſundrie manners according to the perſon, the cauſe and the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">If the noble man be not of authority.</note>For if a mans better, being a noble perſon (not bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the counſell) ſhall in ſcornefull woords chalenge his inferiour for any thing of offence toward him, the inferiour ought by all meanes (not abaceing himſelfe too mutch) to eſcuſe the matter. Or if it be a fault (ſuche as he can yéelde no reaſon for the committing of it) to yéelde with requeſt of pardon. But if either the eſcuſe will not be taken, or that the inferiour had iuſt cauſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommit the offence, and that therevpon the nable man breake out in termes of repreche, as knaue, or lie: it may very well be anſwered <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I neither am knaue, nor lie any more then you, take it as you lift, <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lorde, I know you are a noble man, you may peraduenture ouermatch me with your traine, and yet I muſt ſcamble as well as I can too: Theſe termes be very vnſitting, you muſt either forbeare them, or giue me leaue te thinke too, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11108:13"/>Your Lordſhip may beſtow theſe liueries on thoſe that liue by you, and cannot liue without you: if you will not haue me forget you, forget not your ſelf, for I am much afeard I ſhall reſpect the villanie you offer me aboue the dignitie of your eſtate: But if a great perſonage ſhall reprooue one for any faulte, then media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of freinds, and humble woords, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſorie your L. ſhould grow to theſe termes: I neither am ſuch, nor deſerue to be ſo called of you: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you be to great a ſtate for me to contend with, but if the proudeſt he in this land being mine equall, or not ſo much my better ſhould vſe me ſo, if I did not my beſt to teache him better manner, you might well publiſh me for ſutche as you call me: but I will beare all theſe and be glad of your L. fauour if I may get it, if not I muſt liue like a poore man, and doo as I may, <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lord, theſe be verie ill termes to offer to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: and I muſt tell, you offer them to him that would not beare them at many mens hands, but I muſt beare them at yours, For I confeſſe you bee able to ouermatche me: your traine is longer then mine: if I had thought you would haue vſed me thus, your Lordſhip ſhould haue pardoned me for comming to you at that time.</p>
               <p>Now it is to be conſidered that wordes all this while as they breake no boanes (ſo from one mutche a mans better) they be no great diſgraces: and a man may be compted the wiſer to forbeare, where he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he ſhall by power and rowtes of men or kindred, be ouermatched. But if the beſt vnder a Councellour ſhould giue a blowe, a man ſhalbe aſhamed, if he doo not his beſt to reache him another, whatſoeuer come of it.</p>
               <p>Now if betwéene equals, reproachefull words do riſe, it muſt be diſtinguiſhed <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11108:14"/>If I giue one occaſion of offence that toucheth but his profit, and he giue me reprochefull names for it, as the Lie, or Knaue: I muſt for my credit ſake, not only requite thoſe words with like woords, but counte the wrong mine:<note place="margin">The beſt way to this is to lende him a blowe.</note> and either offer the firſt blowe (if the place ſerue for it) or els chalenge him into the feild: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I can (for pollicie ſake) driue him to chalenge me to ſaue my ſelfe from the danger of the lawe.</p>
               <p>For fighting quarels neuer are made for profit, but for honour: and therefore whatſoeuer hurt be doone, not touching credit, the quarell muſt be his that receiueth the firſt reprochefull words: ſo touching the cauſe, the right conſideration is this: If I offer the firſt reproche, diſdaine, or diſpite, the quarell is the others: his parte it is to chalenge, and I néede not to my equall to make the chalenge. But if the other giue me the firſt lie, or like diſgrcae, it is not inough to ſay he lyeth againe: but I muſt néeds offer a blow, or chalenge the féeild.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">But yet the villany may be ſuch as he may ſtraine good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note>In the houſe of his fréend, I meane in the dyning place at the bourde, or where any aſſembly is, a man may not offer a blowe: but if he haue cauſe giuen him, he ſhall doo well to make ſhewe in woords that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beareth the preſent occaſion, reſpecting the diſturbance of the companie.</p>
               <p>This is no place to growe in termes in, if it were you would not be ſo braue, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe be too great villanies to be borne, if it were not in mine owne houſe, where thou knoweſt I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to eate thée vp, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No into woords, this matter ſhallbe eaſed anon you ſhall ſée, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thanke you ſyr, nay take your pleaſure, I could rayle too, but then I ſhould be like ſuch a raſcall as thy ſelfe, tell me this ſoone if thou ſée I forget it: but if I doo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11108:14"/>take me for ſuch a cowardly boye as I will take thée for, till thou méete me in ſuch a place, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it were not for troubling this companie, I would be your caruer of a péece of my Dagger: but doubt not but I ſhall finde a time for you. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Away raſcall with thy villanous words, I heare by thy great boaſte I ſhall paſſe my iourney quietly at ſuch an hower, in ſuch a place, I know, I ſhall haue cauſe to report thée for a good quiet fellow: I, no more a doo, you know my minde.</p>
               <p>But to conclude in this, I ſhall aduiſe the yonge Gentleman to enforme himſelfe afore he haue neede by enquerie at their hands, that the experienced in that trade, that when he hath neede he may not only be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of courage, but alſo of woordes, phraſe and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to it curragiouſly: and in the ſtouteſt and ſéemlieſt manner for all that I haue written hithertoo of this matter, hath bin rather to ſhew that in euery thing there is a meane to be vſed, in one ſorte to inferiours: and in another ſorte to ſuperiours and equals: to the ende to prouoke him to learne the right manner, then of a meaning, to ſhew any ſkill of mine in the ſame, belonging nothing to my profeſſion: and therefore I will now ſay ſomething how he ſhall take the ieſtings, the prayſyngs, and the thankes of hia ſuperiours and equals, as things that are bothe fitter for me to write, and ſhall of him be oftner and ſooner put in practiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt I will diſcriue ſome ſundrie manner of ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, One is, when a man will charge his famillier freinde (a mans famillier may be either his equall or his better, that liſt of curteſie to become his equall, or one ſomewhat his inferiour to whom he liſt by like curteſie to make his equall) with ſome ill matter that all the companie knoweth to be vntrue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11108:15"/>In that kinde there is no difficultie to anſwere: but it is good to haue varitie of phraſe, and not to anſwer ſtill after one manner: to his mere equall <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You doo well to exerciſe your tongue in matters of no trouth, you may hap els to be taken for a lie teller. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go too, you will haue euery bodie ſée what a lauiſh tongued fellow you be, that cannot ſo much as kéepe counſell of that he knoweth not, what would he doo thinke you of that he knoweth? <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay I dare ſay you would faine haue it beléeued, for it gréeueth him that any man ſhould be taken for honeſter man than himſelfe, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go too, you were beſt leaue your tatling, leaſt I fall a telling of true tales, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay tell on, for I am ſure all is Goſpell that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of thoſe lippes of yours, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is nothing finely handled of you, you ſhould haue ſayd ſumthing that had caried ſome likelyhoode with it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go too, I will make you no more of my counſell ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you be ſuch a blab, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is this the truſt you performe with your fréendes, to tell all and more too? <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Houlde thy peace foole, for my honeſtie is ſo well knowen, as no body here will beléeue thée.</p>
               <p>¶ Now in the like caſe to a mans better muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther phraſes, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay truthe ſyr I haue béen taken for a ſore fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low at that, when I was a yongeman, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If my credit were not very good, this were inough to diſgrace me quite, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be true that you ſay, but I warrant you I handle the matter ſo cunningly, that there is no proofe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11108:15"/>to be had of it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were great pittie any body ſhould doubt of that matter, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus a mans credit is put in daunger by you, if the hearers be not the more fauourable, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some meaſure other mens trades by theyr owne, but I would be lothe any body ſhould thinke I meane ſo by you.</p>
               <p>¶ An other kinde of ieſting with a mans freind is, when they charge him to haue ſayd or donne ſomething of a thirde perſon, that onely himſelfe and his freinde knoweth to be fayned: but yet it may be tould with ſutch a reſemblance of truth, as the hearers may doubt whether it be true or no. In this caſe alſo it is not good to make deniall: but to vſe ſome ſuch phraſe or rountenance as the hearers may perceiue he maketh ſo little accounte of it, as it néedeth no eſcuſe or denial, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You haue loſt mutch good labour now, if you be not beléeued, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſell this good cheape, ſéeing it is of your owne making, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I like you well, for I ſée you loue to make the beſt of any thing, euer, when you wote not how to make the woorſt, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you beléeue him in this, and you ſhall ſée he will take ſuch a pride in it, that he will quoyne you new ſtuffe euery day. <hi>Or to a mans better:</hi> Very well, you may ſay that and more too, if it pleaſe you, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt looke with a ſadder countenance when you wilbe beléeued.</p>
               <p>¶ An other kinde is when they will touche one with ſomething which is true: and though it be no great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11108:16"/>yet it may be ſomewhat that a man would bee loathe to confeſſe, and yet as loathe to be taken for a denier of that which is knowen to be true. In this caſe a man may anſwer <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You doo but dreame peraduentuoe, when you wake you ſhall finde it otherwiſe, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Loe, now you haue heard ſay ſo: and béeing of a good faith, you béeleeued it ſtraight. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Naye no doubt but it muſt needes be true, if you ſay it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did I: you ſpeake your pleaſure, a good tale in déede if it were long inough. <hi>Or to your better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe and like ſpeches with altringe only the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may ſerue in ſport or betweene ſport and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, if a man like not to be ieſted with.</note>This is but ſome malicious tongue, that hath foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this in your eares, I am ſure you doo not beleeue it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay you may ſay what pleaſeth you, for I will doo ſo mutch as confeſſe it, rather then you ſhould not bee beléeued, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I perceiue you minde to make me beholding to you for giuing me ſo good report, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know ſyr your good woord is euer at hand for your freinds, and I perceiue by this that I am one of them, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am bound to you alwaies, I truſt to be able one way or other to make you amends, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No I warrant you, there ſhall no man be able to catche me in ſuch a fault, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well this you would doo if a mans marriage lay on it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, when I lacke one to ſpeake well for mee, I knowe where to finde him at a néede. <hi>Or shus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you looke ſo ſadly, you will make them beléue you in deede.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11108:16"/>¶ An other kinde of ieſting is, when one praiſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for well handling of any matter, either in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or dooing, that in deede hath not beene well, or not ſo well or wiſely as it might haue béene: whereby the other knoweth he ſpeaketh by contraries, this is to bee aunſwered diuerſly, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe if another time you lacke one to doo ſuche a thing finely, it is but ſending for me, and you ſhalbe ſped, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a ſigne you haue a good inſight with you, for I may tell to you, and yet I would be lothe to vaunt too: it was verye excellentlye well done in déede, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, ye ſée I loue not to bragge: but when I doo a thing very wiſely, I loue ſutche fréendes as wyll tell me of it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O naye, but if you had had the handling of it, it would haue beene exquiſitiuely doone. <hi>Or to a mans better thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, if a man chaunce to ſhew all the wit he hath in dooing of a thing, were it reaſon there ſhould be any more required? <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I may tell to you, I did it withall the prouiſion of wit I had at that time in ſtore, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Naye, I truſt I ſhall neuer ſurfet with dooing too wiſely, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I loue not to diſſemble with my fréends, I meane to ſhew them all my wit at once.</p>
               <p>To conclude, in any thing that may ſéeme to carry ſome defect in the dooing, if the doer can himſelfe either with wit turne it to ſome merrie conceit, or els helpe merely to mocke him, himſelfe for companie: it wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare either no defect, or els to be committed rather by careleſneſſe, then for want of wit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11108:17"/>Another kinde of ieſting is to praiſe a man to his face of things that be true in déede: as for his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, his wit, his qualities, his good nature, or his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and whether this be ſpoken in ſporte, or in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, it is all one: for a man muſt euer take vpon him as though all praiſes were ſpoken in ieſt: by which meanes he may in ſporte arrogate them all to himſelfe, with leſſe glorie, then if with taking it in earneſt hee ſhould endeuour to put them from him. So as all ſutch praiſes may bée aunſwered thus with a ſmiling grace.</p>
               <p>Go too, you thinke now that I wyll doo as mutche for you: and ſo I would if I thought you as woorthy of it as I: but you muſt bate me an ace of that, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In déede I muſt confeſſe it is ſo: and you that want ſome of theſe rare giftes, which I am endowed with muſt be contented too, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay true, there be many proper fellowes of the name of vs, if ye knew them, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things be but trifles with me, in compariſon of that I could doo if I liſt, <hi>Ot thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You néede ſay no more, for I warrant you, I beléeue all this to be true, and mutche more. <hi>Or to a mans better, thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thanke you for ſaying ſo, for I hope ſome bodye here will beleeue it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take héede ſyr, that you make not mee ſo beléeue you herein, better then you beluées your ſelfe: for I tell you, it will be harde to make mes thinke the contrarie. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beware what you ſaye, for it lyeth in you to bringe me in as greate an errour as this comes too, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know you will ſaye nothing, but that you bée
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11108:17"/>ſure is true: and therfore, I meane bothe to beléeue it my ſelfe, and alſo to perſwade the audience to bée of a right faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall anſwer to the praiſe and thanks and curteſies ſeriouſly offered by his beters or equals.</head>
               <head>The third Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He praiſe that any man ſhall giue his fréeinds to his face, proceeding of his owne iudgement,<note place="margin">Any prayſes or thankes require ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a ſmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling grace then too ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, though it be a mans better.</note> in earneſt and fréendly wiſe, as one fréende maye in ſome order (in vttering either his owne affection, or to encourage the other without touche of flatterie) doo to an other: it may be anſwered to his equall fréeind, dooing it of good faith, in parte as I haue preſcribed before towards his better, in dooing the like in mirthe. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I may not take your praiſe for any thing, for the goodwill you beare me, blindes you. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you looke better into me, and when you finde how much you be deceiued, tell me of it, that I maye amende it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If another ſhould tell me ſo muche, I ſhould thinke he mockes me: but you may mocke me indéede, and paſſe vneſpied, for the goodwill I thinke you beare me.</p>
               <p>To a ſtranger, that ſhall praiſe him, or ſéeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a good opinion of him <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were beſt (I thinke) neuer to be better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with you, leaſt I make you of another opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:11108:20"/>I thanke you for your good opinion, I would I could beguile euerie body ſo conning as to make them of the ſame minde. <hi>And to a mans better, thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How muche ſoeuer I ſhall want in this, my redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bée at your commaundement ſhall ſupplie it, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The good opinion, whiche rather my good hap, then my deſerts hath wrought in you, cauſeth you (I thinke) to beeléeue that to be in mee, which you wiſh to bee in mee. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I account my hap good, that it pleaſeth you, but to ſay thus mutch: for at the leaſt, I ſhalbe aſhamed of as mutch as I finde wanting here of in my ſelfe, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but take this as a freindly curteſy, by pollicie to encourage mée to ſeeke the attainment of that which I am borne in hand to haue alreadie. Theſe and like, anſweres may be applied alſo to ſutche as ſhall bringe to his eares the good reportes of his fréeindes giuen out of him behinde his backe (as they terme it.) Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that hée picke them out according to the diſtinction of perſons beefore deſcribed: and withal, as it is to bee conſydered that all thinges ſpoken in a ſhowe of mirth though it ſeeme to the hearer ſomwhat ſharpe (and peraduenture anger him) is yet to bée diſſembled and anſwered merely.<note place="margin">In all other entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſeriouſly, a gladſome looke is a better grace then a flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſmile.</note> So whenſoeuer a man in any thing that hee may atribute, truly to himſelfe is praiſed to his face, though it bee ſpoken earneſtly and of good meaning: hée ought alſo, in his foreſaide manner of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres: to ſhew ſutche a ſmilynge grace, as it may appeare hée taketh it as ſpoken rather of their curteſie, then for any cauſe he finds in himſelfe why they ſhould ſo ſay, in ſpeeche (for the moſt parte) the countenance, the grace, and ſounde in the pronunciation is able with one ſelfe ſentence, without altring woorde or ſillable,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11108:20"/>to pleaſe or diſpleaſe others, to ſhew himſelfe wiſe, or make him for ſo mutche to ſéeme fooliſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> affirmeth, that there is nothing that more trieth the wit of man, then the hearing of his owne praiſe: for ſaith he, the wiſe man is put too his triall, when he is praiſed to his face. And therefore for this matter I conclude, that foraſmuch as many times it is harde to finde who ſpeaketh of flatterie contrarie to his thought: who by way of mockerie, though he knowe he ſay true, to trie him, and who of good zeale to ſhew af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and to encourage him: The ſureſt way in this doubt is (except to thoſe whoſe fréendſhip by other meanes he hath experience of) to vſe his anſwers ſo, as he may make them earneſt or ſporte at his pleaſure, as he perceiueth their aſſeueracion to prouoke him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall acquite himſelfe towards no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons, that ſhall either for his freendes ſake, or his owne, offer him curteſies: or aſſure him of freeindſhip, willing him in all chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be bolde with him.</head>
               <head>¶ The .iiii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this caſe as in all other of intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the inferiour muſt note in what manner, whether ſeriouſlye or familliarly, ſuch curteſie or intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be offred him: and thereafter to chuſe out and ſhape out anſwers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to eche kinde: for the firſt, if he be a ſtraunger to him: but not to his freends <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I knowe ſutche, or ſutch of my fréendes ſo mutche béeholding to you too, as hath bin ſufficient to binde me
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11108:19"/>to honour and loue you: and ſéeing it pleaſeth you to extend your curteſie alſo towards me, I can but wiſh my ſeruice, as ſufficient as my good will is: to aſſure you too, of my thankefull minde, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lorde, I can but acknowledge that debte for my ſelfe; which before I thought to owe for others of my fréends, that haue taſted of your curteſie: but I am glad that I may by this meanes ſhew it, which your Lordſhip ſhall finde me ready to doo, wherein ſoeuer I ſhall thinke my ſeruice may be acceptable, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this your Lordſhips goodnes riſeth of your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie without any deſertes, ſo muſt I confeſſe my ſelfe euer vnable to counterpeyſe it: I can but acknowledge my ſelfe too mutch bound to you for it: and double bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d if it ſhall pleaſe you to commaund me to the vttermoſt of my power, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly thanke your Lordſhip, I can but requite it with my ſeruice, and that I beſéech you commaund, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My humble thankes are but an vnequall recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and therefore I ſhall deſire your L. to put my gratefull minde in triall, by commaunding my ſeruice, <hi>Or ſhortly, thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If my ſeruice may any way be ought woorth, if I may but vnderſtande it, it ſhall not néede to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly thanke your L. and I beſéech you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund me, as your ſeruant, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly thanke your L. and I beſéeche you thinke that you voutchſafe this curteſie on him that will be as readie to requite it with the vttermoſt of his ſeruice, as he that is better ſtored of woords. The vſe of long or ſhort ſentences muſt be imployed according as he ſéeth the hearer at leaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11108:19"/>
               <head>¶ How when the foreſayde ſpeeches bee offered by a noble perſon pleſantly, that is of acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which muſt be alſo pleaſantly anſwered.</head>
               <head>The .v. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lorde, you know I haue no ſtore of eloquence: but what mayme ſo euer you finde in my vtterance, I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you ſhall finde none in my good will, whenſoeuer I may doo you anye ſeruice, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly thanke your Lordſhip, I warrant you I make ſo ſure reckoning thereof, as I am more like to be boulde of your curteſie, then to requeſt it: but I muſt pray your Lordſhip to thinke that ſhall be rather for want of power then of good will, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Lordſhip muſt be content with my humble thankes for this time: but I would be very ſorie to thinke your Lordſhip made not accompt of me, as of him whom you may moſt commaund, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lord I haue had ſo good experience of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer curteſies, bothe towards me and other my fréends, as I had néede with my ſeruice to goe about to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence ſome parte of that, before I come in debt for any more: But the leſſe we can requite, the more we muſte ſtand bounde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to an equall, or but little better beeing a freend and familliar.</head>
               <head>¶ The .vi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11108:18"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O our fréend thus:</p>
               <p>I am in your debt for ſo mutch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie as if you lende me any more, you will make me bankroute: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée with you for the tenthe parte, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You offer me ſo mutche, and I can requite ſo little: as I ſee, you meane to make me an ill debter ſtill, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know I haue no curious woords in ſtoare, but in plaine termes. I thanke you, and will requite it if I can, <hi>Or ſeriouſly thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I praye you thinke, that though I vſe not manye woordes with you, I thinke my ſelfe ſo much beholding to you: as wherein I may pleaſure you, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde me not. I ſhall thinke you loue me not. <hi>Or to a ſtraunger thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Syr I thanke you of this curteſie, if it ſhall lie in me to requite it, I pray you be as boulde with me, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir I muſt be your debter for this curteſie, till time and place ſerue to requite it: but in the meane time I thanke you, I pray you make the like accompt of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall take thankes of a noble perſon.</head>
               <head>The .vii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>IF thankes be offered in ſerious manner and for any waightie matter <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lorde, it was my goodwill, as well as my dutie, to haue done it to your beſt contentation: but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11108:18"/>if there be any defect in it, I pray your Lordſhip impute it to mine vnſkilfulneſſe. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lord it is no reaſon that you thanke him, whom you ought to commaund: and ſpecially me, that am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſatiſfie for the tenthe parte of that dewtie or goodwill I owe you: but if there be ought done to your contentation, or that haue pleaſed you, I am very well a paide and ſufficiently thanked, <hi>Or if merely thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray you kéepe your thankes for a thing more woorthy them: for if your Lordſhip beſtowe ſo manie thankes for ſo ſmall matters, you will make me looke for too manie when I ſhall doo you any better ſeruice.</p>
               <p>¶ To a mans equall fréeind, or but little his better, <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay ſir, you will marre me, if you giue me too many thankes: for then you will bring me more in debt for my thankes, that I am yours for this matter by a great deale, <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doo fréeinds vſe this curioſitie in giuing thankes, I am ſure it is but to teach me good manners againſt an other time, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I praye you keepe thankes for ſtraungers, and let me know whether it were to your liking or not, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You be at too muche coſt for ſo ſmall a matter: I know now where to haue thankes another time when I deſerue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man maye giue thankes to his betters and equals.</head>
               <head>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:11108:21"/>The .viii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F my humble thankes were a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent recompence to your Lordſhip, I ſhould not reſt ſo muche in your debt as now I am bound to doo, for ſuch a curteſie, &amp;c. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lorde, I haue humble thankes to render, for ſuch a matter which did me great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but they be ſo vnequall a requitall, as I were beſt to ad this to the reſt of your curteſies or goodneſſe, and ſtande bound for the whole, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſo muche bound to your Lordſhip, for ſutch a thing, &amp;c. As I muſt thinke all the ſeruice I can doo too little woorthe in reſpect of your goodneſſe ſhewed therein.</p>
               <p>To a mans fréend <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am too muche in your debte, to giue you thankes for ſutche a thinge, &amp;c. For till I can make ſome ſhew in déedes, I will come vpon the ſcore with you in words, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though thankes be not inough for this pleaſure that you haue doone me: yet I pray you allow of them till I be able to make better paiment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ What manners be requiſite at the Table, and what to bee ſhunned: for, what is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the waſhing before Dinner, and in the ſitting downe, is ſet foorth in the beginning of this Direction.</head>
               <head>¶ The .ix. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11108:21"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to pauſe when a man is ſet, and with leaſure to vnfolde his Napkin, wipe his Knife, cut his breade,<note place="margin">This cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie is not to be vſed, but when a man fitteth at the vpper meſſe with his betters, or at the ſecond, when either the maiſter of the houſe ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth there, or ſome noble perſon.</note> and there to ſlay till either his better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, or make countenance to him to eate where he liſt: and then to begin, not at the diſh that ſhall ſtand right before his better, except it be offered him: neither of the daintieſt meates which (lightly) ſtande loweſt: but to chuſe ſome ſutche diſhe to be dooing on the while, till he ſee whether his better will chuſe or refuſe ſome other diſhe, that he had rather eate on.</p>
               <p>Item to haue an eye to ſutche as ſit next beneath him and cannot reach, and peraduenture for good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (if they be any thing his inferiours) wil not ſpeake: and if they eate not, to aſke whether he ſhalbe their Caruer. But I would not haue him to be any mans Caruer, without aſking him firſt, except it be to one ſo much his inferiour, as he knoweth will be glad of the curteſy he ſheweth him, though he like not the meate. For as to Carue to a mans better is a preſumption, ſo to ones equall, except by aſking firſt the queſtion, you know it wilbe welcome to him, wilbe taken for too mutche ſawning, except alſo that for the daintineſſe of the meate, or fine chuſing of the beſt morſell, he offreth it to his very familier freind, by way of a curteous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: for a man muſt for a generall rule, take héede that in a ſtraunge place he be not to buſie in offering ſeruice, or curteſies, though it be to his betters: but in a mans owne houſe or his Fathers, it cannot lightly be too mutche.</p>
               <p>Item if a man be in his owne houſe, or his Fathers, where it becommeth him to giue countenance or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment he may to his equall, and ſuch as be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what his inferiours, he may the oftner proffer them
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11108:22"/>this or that meate, and drink to them, but not too much. For if a man euery time he drinketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall drinke to one or other,<note place="margin">It is counted a fooliſh grace euer to drinke to ſome body, and ſpecially at the firſt draught.</note> it wilbe ſéene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as though he did it for lacke of countenance: ſo that to vſe the ſalutacion of the Cup aboue twiſe in one meale, wilbee too mutche, except the whole companie fall to quaffing. For wiſe men doo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeke to ſatiſfy their gueſts with ſome good ſpéeches then with ſuch dum ſygues.</p>
               <p>This kinde of Cup greeting ought not to bee vſed but in one of theſe two reſpects: either to make our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour (to whom we meane not to vſe ſpéeche of famil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie) to thinke we will doo them a curtefie: or els to our very fréende by way of congratulation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man muſt neuer drinke to his better, except he be ſure that by way of fréendſhip and familliarite he be content to become his equall, and that not with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem or ſad countenance, but with ſome ſmiling grace, that the reſt may knowe it procéedeth of familiaritie, and not of preſumption, yet with reuerent woords and chaunge of phraſe, <hi>as thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lorde, if ſome yonge Nobleman:</p>
               <p>Sir, or Madam, will it pleaſe you to giue me leaue. <hi>Or thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall I be ſo boulde as ſalute you with this Cup of Wine. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By your leaue ſyr, againſt it next pleaſe you. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will you giue me leaue to remember ſuch a one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſome fréend of his. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To plucke you out of your ſtudies. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sauing your tale ſyr.</p>
               <p>Item, that aboue all thinges in a ſtraunge place, or in the preſence of ſtraungers, he attend not ſo gréedely, nor ſo continually to his feeding: but that in modeſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11108:22"/>wiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> either gazing too longe in another mans face: or yet hanging his head continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: he hath both his eye and his eare ſo redy, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſaide or doone at the bourde, but he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, for his learning, that good is to follow, that ill is to eſchew. And when he ſeeth any thing vncomely, to examine himſelfe, whether he haue not the ſame grace himſelfe: and alſo to doo the like, whenſoeuer he heareth any man diſpraiſed. For moſt men know what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or vncomely in another: But many for lacke of due obſeruation in themſelues, mocke or dyſpraiſe in another, the ſame which others mock in them: and the rather for their ſo dooing.</p>
               <p>Item, that he pawſe betwéene meate and meate, and neuer to carue himſelfe, either of meate or bread, while his mouth is full: nor till he haue ſwallowed the laſt morſell.</p>
               <p>Item that he fill not his mouthe ſo full of meate as he cannot holde his lippes together while he is chaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for other wiſe, men ſhall looke into his mouthe, and ſee the meate rowle vp and downe while he is eatinge: which is a fowle ſight, and loatheſome: and for that cauſe, a man muſt forbeare to ſpeake with meate in his mouthe, except he haue ſo little, as he bee ſure to hide it in his mouthe while he is ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>Item, while his better telleth him any tale, to ceaſe eating: bethe while he heareth, and while he anſwereth him.</p>
               <p>Item, if he be prouoked to laughe in the preſence of his betters to doo the ſame with as little noyſe as may be: and likewiſe in the company of ſtraungers, for too lowde a laughter, ſpecially, for ſlender occaſions, doo make wiſemen counted fooliſh of ſutch as know them not.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:11108:23"/>Item, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man will tell a mery tale let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſelfe be not the firſt that ſhall laughe at it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſmiling ſound to make men know he ſpeaketh but in ſporte, is good: but a fained laughter is ill becomming. A hartie laughter (ſo the matter be worth it) is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>Item he muſt beware that while another tell a tale, or make ieſtures: that his wits be not caried away, ſo as he gaze continually in his face, and make the ſame countenances which he ſéeth the other doo: for that will make a man counted doultiſh.</p>
               <p>Item if he be conſtrained to yawne, teache, belche, cough, ſnéeſe, clenſe the noſe, or ſpit either at the bourde, or in the preſence of his betters or ſtraungers: he muſt ſuppreſſe the ſound, and ſhadow the ſight, as muche as he may conuiently without making it to nice.</p>
               <p>Item in caruing himſelfe or others, he muſt not embrew too many of his fingers, nor his thombe: nor wallow his meate vp and down to much in the ſauce, becauſe in ſo dooing a man ſhall waſhe his fingers in the ſaufe, which others will loathe, ſpecially ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p>Now to conclude, though a man either at home or among his fréends, may vſe what manner he liſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſeruing all theſe ceremonies: yet it ſhalbe verye good ſomwhat to enure himſelfe by dayly cuſtome: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he ſhall in preſence forgette bothe them and himſelfe</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall pacifie his freeind, his better, or his equall: if he haue giuen him vnwillinglye any cauſe of offence.</head>
               <head>¶ The .x. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11108:23"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F for a light cauſe, then merely <hi>thus:</hi> I am ſure you take it not in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, or thinke I meant otherwiſe then in the beſt part: for if you doo, you ſhall doo me great wronge, <hi>Or thus:</hi> By my trouthe I did, or ſaide it to no ſuch ende, as you take it: and therefore I pray you thinke of it, as I meant it. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I had thought it could haue bin ſo much miſtaken, I would haue bin more wary: but let it ſuffice you that I ment but well and fréeindly, for otherwiſe I did it not I aſſure you: Or carneſtly for ſome greater matter, <hi>then thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My hap is ill, that of ſo good a meaning, ſhould fall out ſo ill conceiuing, or ſo ill ſucceſſe: for that I did or ſayde, was as I would haue doone to my very fréende, or would haue had doone to my ſelfe, it reſtes in your choice to beléeue me: but if you doo not, you ſhall wronge your ſelfe, as well as me, in miſtruſting me without a cauſe, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I can but tell you and aſſure you on my faithe, I meant thus, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I haue giuen you any cauſe to thinke other wiſe, or if it haue fallen out contrarie to mine expectation: I am not only ſoarie for it, but I will be readie to make any recompence I can, <hi>Or to ones better thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly ſir, it was not my intent to doo herein anye thing that might offende: but I will yéelde, that it is fault mough that I vſed no more circumſpection, but that you may conceiue ill of it: you néede not to giue me any penance, for that my repentance is ſo murche, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you knew my minde, you would put me in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11108:24"/>truſt for reuenging this faut: for I ſhall be angrie with my ſelfe this good while for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How a man ſhall ſhift of reproches or tauntes offred betweene ſporte and earneſt, by enuious and ſcornefull perſons, that will ſeeme to doo it ſo cunninglye, as the other ſhall haue the taunt, and yet at his owne pleaſure will denie it.</head>
               <head>The .xi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He beſt way is, if he can touche the ſame party as néere, without ſéeming to be angrie: but if he know nothing perticulerly to charge him or to mock him withall, then, to ſcorne him bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene ſporte &amp; anger againe, <hi>as thus:</hi> Oh finely handled, were you borne ſo. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ieſus who would haue thought you coulde haue throwen ſo harde to hit your ſelfe, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare ſay, you weene you haue ſpoken very trimly now. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You haue made a great ſpeake ſir, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is quoth you, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thanke you of your coſt, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is but your good nature to take or expounde it ſo. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I remember I deſired you not to ſay that for me: but yet you ſhall finde me too kinde harted to dye in your debt. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did any bodye teache you to ſay ſo, or comes it of your mother wit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11108:24"/>¶ Now if they ſhall replie, and go about to make it ſéeme they meane ſimply, <hi>then thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare ſay you doo, and therefore I thanke you as hartely. <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why I truſt you thinke not that I doubte of that, <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why I take it ſo and therefore I commend you for it and ſo turne it to mirthe agayne, if the other will needs haue it ſo. But if the other will proſecute it with ſharpe tauntes, vnder a fléeryng or laughing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>then thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Naye I am not ſkilled in ieſters arte, tell me your minde in earneſt, and you ſhall finde me ready to make you ſuch ſporte as I dare: <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will tell you, if you will néedes become a Ieſter to make Gentlemen ſporte: It were beſt to call ſome other to helpe countenance you, that is of your facultie, for in faith I am nothing apt for you at this time.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Ihones, dwelling at the Signe of the Roſe and Crowne, neere Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Bridge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
